Guide to the Benjamin Lee Whorf Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Benjamin Lee Whorf papers
1898-1971
MS 822
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
9.5
(23 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence; writings on linguistics, science and religion; miscellaneous biographical material; and lantern slides. Nearly three-fourths of the papers consist of Benjamin Whorf's writings on linguistics, including drafts of published works, unpublished manuscripts, research notes on his trip to Mexico in 1930 and on Hebrew, Maya, Hopi and other languages. Also included are articles by others, chiefly on Indian languages. The correspondence, which is entirely professional, includes Franz Boas, Frans Blom, Clyde Kluckhohn, Alfred Kroeber, J. Alden Mason, Edward Sapir, Herbert Spinden, Alfred M. Tozzer, George L. Trager and Charles F. Voegelin.
Whorf, Benjamin Lee, 1897-1941
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Celia Peckham Whorf in 1975, John B. Carroll in 1978, and Celia W. Wheeler, 2006 and 2011.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Series I-IV, except for boxes 3, 9, 12, and 13, are available on microfilm; patrons must use FILM HM 98 instead of the originals.
Existence and Location of Copies
Series I-IV, except for boxes 9-13 are also available on microfilm (6,465 frames on 5 reels, 35mm.) from Scholarly Resources, Inc., Wilmington, Delaware. HM 98
Arrangement
Arranged in five series and two additions: I. Correspondence. I. Writings on Linguistics. III. Writings on Science and Religion. IV. Biographical Information. V. Lantern Slides.
Scope and Contents
The Benjamin Lee Whorf Papers consist of six linear feet of correspondence, writings, research material, and biographical matter. They span the entire period of his adult linguistic activity, from about 1923 until his death in 1941, and include posthumous letters and publications as well. The papers are arranged in five series: I. Correspondence; II. Writings on Linguistics; III. Writings on Science and Religion; IV. Biographical Information; V. Lantern Slides.
Series I., CORRESPONDENCE, consists of Benjamin Whorf's correspondence between 1925 and 1941 and letters received by his widow, Celia Peckham Whorf, between 1941 and 1954. The letters written and received by Whorf offer substantive discussions of the full range of his linguistic interests. Among the leading correspondents are Franz Boas, Frans Blom, Clyde Kluckhohn, Alfred Kroeber, J. Alden Mason, Edward Sapir, Herbert Spinden, Alfred M. Tozzer, George L. Trager, and Charles F. Voegelin.
Series II., WRITINGS ON LINGUISTICS, consists of notes, drafts, and printed matter documenting Whorf's linguistic activities from his first explorations in Hebrew around 1924 to the publication of a Spanish edition of Language, Thought, and Reality in 1971. There are four sections: Published Writings, Unpublished Writings, Research Notes, and Writings by Others.
Published Writings consists of manuscript and printed versions of slightly less than half of Whorf's publications on language and a small quantity of related notes and research material. The majority of the handwritten drafts and a few of the typewritten drafts differ slightly from the printed text.
Unpublished Writings consists of lectures, research reports, and unpublished essays on particular languages (principally Hebrew, Nahuatl, Maya, and Hopi) and general linguistic questions. Most of the titles in Carroll's bibliography are represented, and there are more than a dozen items that do not appear in his selection.
Research Notes consists of material connected with Whorf's linguistic studies. The notes are related to his Mexican research trip in 1930 and to his studies in Hebrew, Maya, Hopi, and several other languages.
Writings by Others consists of other scholars' publications annotated by Whorf.
Series III., WRITINGS ON SCIENCE AND RELIGION, consists mainly of essays on the relationship between science and religion, the nature of the mind end the universe, and the achievements of "primitive" and "advanced" civilizations. There are also published and unpublished writings on fire insurance and notes and writings on botany.
Series IV., BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL, consists of obituaries and other clippings about Benjamin Whorf; photographs of him and Ernest Naquayouma, his Hopi informant; and miscellaneous printed matter related to his personal life and his attendance at scholarly meetings. The principal item of biographical interest, aside from the clippings and photographs, is a program showing that Whorf joined the Methodist Episcopal Church by profession of faith in 1923.
Series V., LANTERN SLIDES, consists of views of Central American landscapes, artifacts, hieroglyphs, and historic sites.
MICROFILM NOTE:
Series I-IV are available on microfilm, HM 98, and must be used in this format. The printed matter in Published Writings, the notecards in Research Notes, and Writings by Others in Series II were not microfilmed and may be used in the original.
The target at the beginning of Reel 5 mistakenly identifies the material following as being from Series III. Material on frames 1-866 is actually from Series II, WRITINGS ON LINGUISTICS, Research Notes. Series III, WRITINGS ON SCIENCE AND RELIGION, begins, instead, at frame 867. The target at frame 867 incorrectly identifies the material following as being from Series IV. In fact, BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL, Series IV, begins at frame 1363. The target at frame 1363 correctly identifies this material.
Chronology
Benjamin Lee Whorf had a brief but important career as a pioneering scholar of the Nahuatl, Maya, and Hopi languages and as a theoretician about the influence of language on thought and perception. Researchers should consult Language, Thought, and Reality for a biographical sketch and bibliography by John B. Carroll,¹ but these are some principal events and periods in his life:
1897 born in Winthrop, Massachusetts
1918 received the B.S. in chemical engineering from the Massachusetts Institute of Technology
1919-1941 employed as a fire prevention engineer by the Hartford Fire Insurance Company
1920 married Celia Inez Peckham
[1924-1928] studied Hebrew
1925 wrote "Why I Have Discarded Evolution"
1928 read "Aztec Linguistics" and "An Aztec Account of the Period of the Toltec Decline" at the Twenty-Third International Congress of Americanists
1930 took a field trip to Mexico, supported by the Social Science Research Council
1931 began studies with Edward Sapir at Yale University
1932 began his linguistic analysis of Hopi
1933 published The Phonetic Basis of Certain Characters in Maya Writing
1936 published his first article on Hopi, "The punctual and segmentative aspects of Hopi," in Language
1937-1938 was a Lecturer in Anthropology at Yale
1940-1941 published three articles for a non-professional audience in Technology Review
1941 died on July 26 after some months' illness
¹Benjamin Lee Whorf, Language, Thought and Reality: Selected Writings of Benjamin Lee Whorf, Comp. John B. Carroll, (Cambridge, Mass.: The M. I. T. Press, 1956).
American Anthropologist; Codex Dresdensis Maya; Language; Technology review; Hebrew language; Hopi language; Indians of North America; Language and languages; Linguistics; Mayan languages -- Writing; Mayan languages; Nahuatl language; Religion and science -- 1926-1945; Semitic languages; Mexico -- Languages; Bloch, Bernard, 1907-1965; Blom, Frans Ferdinand, 1893-1963; Haas, Mary R. (Mary Rosamond), 1910-1996; Kluckhohn, Clyde, 1905-1960; Kroeber, A. L. (Alfred Louis), 1876-1960; Lesher, Robert A.; Mason, Gregory, 1889-; Mason, John Alden, 1885-1967; Mason, Ruth, 1890-1974; Nykl, A. R. (Alois Richard), 1885-1958; Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939; Schapiro, Benjamin Aaron Moses, 1871?-; Spence, Lewis, 1874-1955; Spier, Leslie, 1893-1961; Spinden, Herbert Joseph, 1879-1967; Swadesh, Morris, 1909-1967; Thompson, Laura, 1905-; Torrey, Charles Cutler, 1863-1956; Tozzer, Alfred M. (Alfred Marston), 1877-1954; Trager, George L. (George Leonard), 1906-1992; Trubet͡skoĭ, Nikolaĭ Sergeevich, kni͡azʹ, 1890-1938; Voegelin, C. F. (Charles Frederick), 1906-1986; Whorf, Benjamin Lee, 1897-1941; American Anthropological Association; Carnegie Institution of Washington; Linguistic Society of America; Massachusetts Institute of Technology; Science Service, Inc; Social Science Research Council (U.S.); Society for American Indian Linguists; Theosophical Society in America; Westinghouse Electric Corporation; Yale University. Secretary's Office; American Scientific Congress (8th) -- Washington, D.C. -- 1940; International Congress of Americanists (23rd) -- New York, N.Y. -- 1928
- Correspondence, 1926-1954; Series I; .75 linear feet (2 boxes)
  Arrangement
  The arrangement is chronological.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Materials in this series are available on microfilm; patrons must use FILM HM 98 instead of the originals.
  General
  An alphabetical index of correspondents in this series and in Series II appears at the end of the print register and also at the beginning of Box 1.
  - 1926 - 1939 April (Box 1, Folder 1-20, Reel 1U)
  - 1939 May - 1941 April (Box 2, Folder 21-27, Reel 1U)
  - 1941 July - 1954 (To Mrs. Celia Whorf) (Box 2, Folder 28, Reel 1U)
- Writings on Linguistics, 1924-1971; Series II; 4.5 linear feet (11 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Published Writings and Unpublished Writings are in chronological order. Research Notes is in alphabetical order by language. Writings by Others is in alphabetical order by author.
  The printed matter in Published Writings, the notecards in Research Notes, and Writings by Others in Series II were not microfilmed and may be used in the original.
  Materials in this series, except for boxes 3, 9, 12, and 13, are available on microfilm; patrons must use FILM HM 98 instead of the originals.
  - Published Writings
    - Toltec History, Twenty-Third International Congress of Americanists, Abstracts of Papers: manuscript, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 1, Reel 2U)
    - Aztec Linguistics, Twenty-Third International Congress of Americanists, Abstracts of Papers: typescript, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 1, Reel 2U)
    - An Aztec Account of the Period of the Toltec Decline, Twenty-Third International Congress of Americanists, Proceedings: typescript, reprint, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 2, Reel 2U)
    - The Reign of Huemac, American Anthropologist: typescript, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 3, Reel 2U)
    - A Central Mexican Inscription Combining Mexican and Maya Day Signs, American Anthropologist: manuscript, typescript, reprint illustration, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 4, Reel 2U)
    - Maya Writing and its Decipherment, Maya Research: manuscript, typescript, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 5, Reel 2U)
    - Appendix to J. Alden Mason, "The Classification of the Sonoran Languages," in Robert H. Lowier, ed., Essays in Anthropology in Honor of Alfred Louis Kroeber: reprint, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 6, Reel 2U)
    - Notes on the "Glossary" in Elsie Clews Parsons, Hopi Journal of Alexander M. Stephens, Part 2: manuscript, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 7, Reel 2U)
    - "The Punctual and Segmentative Aspects of Verbs in Hopi," Language: notes, manuscript, typescript, reprint, mailing list for reprints, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 8, Reel 2U)
    - "The Origin of Aztec TL," American Anthropologist: reprint, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 9, Reel 2U)
    - "Some Verbal Categories of Hopi," Language: manuscript, typescript, reprint, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 10, Reel 2U)
    - "Science and Linguistics," Technology Review: reprints, 1940, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 11, Reel 2U)
    - "Linguistics as an Exact Science," Technology Review: reprint, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 12, Reel 2U)
    - "Languages and Logic," Technology Review: reprint, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 13, Reel 2U)
    - "The Relation of Habitual Thought and Behavior to Language," in Leslie Spier, ed., Language, Culture, and Personality: reprint, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 14, Reel 2U)
    - "Decipherment of the Linguistic Portion of the Maya Hieroglyphs," The Smithsonian Report for 1941: abstracts in Spanish and English, reprint, program and leaflets from the Eighth American Scientific Congress, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 15, Reel 2U)
    - "The Hopi Language, Toreva Dialect," in Harry Hoijer, ed., Linguistic Structures of Native America: manuscript, typescript, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 16, Reel 2U)
    - ["On Psychology"], in John B. Carroll, ed., Language, Thought and Reality: Selected Writings of Benjamin Lee Whorf: manuscript, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 17, Reel 2U)
    - "A Linguistic Consideration of Thinking in Primitive Communities," in John B. Carroll, ed., Language, Thought and Reality: notes, manuscript, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 18, Reel 2U)
    - John B. Carroll, ed., Sprache, Denken, Wirrlichreit (German translation of Language, Thought and Reality, 1956), 1963 (Box 3, Folder 19, Reel 2U)
    - John B. Carroll, ed., Linguagio, Pensiero e Realtà (Italian translation of Language, Thought and Reality, 1956), 1970 (Box 3, Folder 20, Reel 2U)
    - John B. Carroll, ed., Lenguaje, Pensamiento y Realidad (Spanish translation of Language, Thought and Reality, 1956), 1971 (Box 4, Folder 21, Reel 2U)
      Materials in box 4 are available on microfilm; patrons must use FILM HM 98 instead of the originals.
  - Unpublished Writings
    Materials in boxes 4 and 5 are available on microfilm; patrons must use FILM HM 98 instead of the originals.
    - A New Conception of Semitic Roots: manuscript, typescript, [1927?] (Box 4, Folder 22, Reel 2U)
    - The Inner Nature of the Hebrew Language: typescript, [1928?] (Box 4, Folder 23, Reel 2U)
    - A Contribution to the Study of Aztec Language: notes, typescript, [1928?] (Box 4, Folder 24, Reel 2U)
    - Investigations in Aztec Linguistics and Toltec History. Part II. The Phenomenon of Oligosynthesis in Nahuatl or Aztec, Twenty-Third International Congress of Americanists: manuscript, typescript, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 25, Reel 2U)
    - Notes on the Oligosynthetic Comparison of Nahuatl and Piman, with Special Reference to Tepecano: notes, typescript, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 26, Reel 2U)
    - Appendix to Notes on the Oligosynthetic Comparison of Nahuatl and Piman (Tepecano): notes, typescript, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 26, Reel 2U)
    - Plan of Project, submitted to the Social Science Research Council: manuscript, typescript, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 27, Reel 2U)
    - Translations from the Annals of Quauhtitlan: typescript, [1928?] (Box 4, Folder 28, Reel 2U)
    - Translation of Aztec MS, Gates Coll. # 758A/1: research material, notes, manuscript, typescript, 1929 (Box 4, Folder 29, Reel 2U)
      See also: Series I, Frans Blom, 1928 Nov 14-1929 Dec 12; box 1, folder 3-5.
      See Also: Series I, Alfred M. Tozzer, 1929 May 7, 13; box 1, folder 4.
    - Conclusion of Report on Research Project, Social Science Research Council: manuscript, typescript, 1930 (Box 4, Folder 30, Reel 2U)
    - Stem Series in Maya and Certain Maya Hieroglyphs, Linguistic Society of America: notes, manuscript, typescript, illustrations, 1930 (Box 4, Folder 31, Reel 2U)
    - Notes on Two Recent Findings from Central Mexico: manuscript, typescript, 1930 (Box 4, Folder 32, Reel 2U)
    - Pitch Tone and the Saltillo in Modern and Ancient Nahuatl: manuscript, 1930 (Box 4, Folder 33, Reel 2U)
    - The Problem of American History Before Columbus, Connecticut Historical Society: notes, manuscript, 1931 (Box 4, Folder 34, Reel 2U)
    - The Structure of the Athabascan Languages: typescript, 1932 (Box 4, Folder 35, Reel 2U)
    - Characteristics of the Uto-Aztecan Stock: notes, typescript, 1932 (Box 4, Folder 36, Reel 2U)
    - The Uto-Aztecan Stock: notes, [1932?] (Box 4, Folder 37, Reel 2U)
    - First Report on Hopi: manuscript, typescript, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 37, Reel 2U)
    - Recent Determinations of Phonetic Characters in Maya Writing, Linguistic Society of America: manuscript, typescript, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 38, Reel 2U)
    - The Phonology of Hopi: manuscript, [1934?] (Box 5, Folder 40, Reel 2U)
    - Hopi Phonemes: typescript, mimeograph, [1934?] (Box 5, Folder 40, Reel 2U)
    - Hopi Text: manuscript, [1934-1935?] (Box 5, Folder 41, Reel 3U)
    - Educational Project: Study of Learning-Inhibitions and their Prevention and Treatment: typescript, 1935 (Box 5, Folder 42, Reel 3U)
    - First Steps in the Decipherment of Maya Writing: manuscript, [1935?] (Box 5, Folder 43, Reel 3U)
    - Outline of Hopi Morphology: typescript, [1935?] (Box 5, Folder 44, Reel 3U)
    - The Hopi Language: manuscript, [1935?] (Box 5, Folder 45, Reel 3U)
      - Hopi Verb Classes: manuscript, 1934 (Box 5, Folder 39, Reel 2U)
    - The Hopi Language: typescript, [1935?] (Box 5, Folder 46, Reel 3U)
    - A Comparative Decipherment of Forty-one Ancient Maya Written Words, American Anthropological Association: manuscript, typescript, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 47, Reel 3U)
    - Notes for the Chemistry of Language and Thought, Hartford Technical Club: notes, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 48, Reel 3U)
    - "Azteco-Tanoan": notes, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 49, Reel 3U)
    - Macro-Penutian: notes, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 50, Reel 3U)
    - Response to circular letter on the status of American linguistics: typescript, mimeograph, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 51, Reel 3U)
    - Classification of the Languages of North America North of Mexico: typescript, 1937, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 52, Reel 3U)
    - Report on Linguistics Research in the Department of Anthropology of Yale University for the term September 1937 to June 1938, with G. L. Trager: manuscript, typescript (Box 5, Folder 53, Reel 3U)
    - The Reading of Maya Glyph C of the Supplementary Series and other Glyphs: notes, manuscript, typescript, [1938?] (Box 5, Folder 54, Reel 3U)
    - Phonemes of the Toreva Dialect of Hopi: manuscript, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 55, Reel 3U)
    - Some Experiments with Language, Wethersfield Rotary Club: manuscript, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 56, Reel 3U)
    - Descrifamiento de la Parte Linguistica de los Jeroglificos Mayas, Eighth American Scientific Congress: mimeograph, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 57, Reel 3U)
    - Maya Vocabulary from Motul Dictionary: manuscript, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 58, Reel 3U)
    - Analysis and Translation of a Short Maya Text in Hieroglyphs, Linguistic Society of America: abstract, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 59, Reel 3U)
    - The Parts of Speech in Hopi: notes, manuscript, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 59, Reel 3U)
    - Notes on Linguistics: Rough Outline of Historical Development of Linguistic Theory: notes, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 60, Reel 3U)
    - Ancient America and the Evolution of the Coming Race: manuscript, undated (Box 5, Folder 61, Reel 3U)
    - Experiment in Linguistic Abstraction and/or Assimilation: typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 62, Reel 3U)
    - First Sketches for Language, Thought and Reality: notes, undated (Box 5, Folder 63, Reel 3U)
    - Glyph Groups Regarded as Proving Phoneticism in the Maya Script: typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 64, Reel 3U)
    - Unidentified transcriptions (related to the Gates manuscript?): manuscript, undated (Box 5, Folder 65, Reel 3U)
  - Research Notes
    Materials in boxes 6-8 and 10-11 are available on microfilm; patrons must use FILM HM 98 instead of the originals.
    The target at the beginning of Reel 5 mistakenly identifies the material following as being from Series III. Material on frames 1-866 is actually from Series II, WRITINGS ON LINGUISTICS, Research Notes.
    - Notes on Aztec, 1929, undated (Box 6, Folder 66, Reel 3U)
    - Notes on Gaelic and Polish, 1927-1930, undated (Box 6, Folder 67, Reel 3U)
    - Notes on Hebrew
      - [1924-1928?] (Box 6, Folder 68, Reel 3U)
      - [1924-1928?] (Box 6, Folder 69, Reel 3U)
      - [1924-1928?] (Box 6, Folder 70, Reel 3U)
      - [1924-1928?] (Box 6, Folder 71, Reel 3U)
      - 1926, [1924-1928?] (Box 6, Folder 72, Reel 4U)
      - 1927, [1924-19282] (Box 6, Folder 73, Reel 4U)
      - 1928, [1924-1928?] (Box 6, Folder 74, Reel 4U)
    - Notes on binary sequences in Hebrew, [1927?] (Box 6, Folder 75, Reel 4U)
    - Notes on binary groups in Hebrew, [1927?] (Box 6, Folder 76, Reel 4U)
    - Notes and charts relating to Hebrew and Semitic roots, 1925, 1927, [1924-1928?] (Box 6, Folder 77, Reel 4U)
    - Notebook on Hopi, 1932 (Box 7, Folder 78, Reel 4U)
    - Notes on Hopi, 1932-1937, [1940?], undated (Box 7, Folder 79, Reel 4U)
    - Notebooks on Hopi
      - 1933-1938 (Box 7, Folder 80-83, Reel 4U)
      - 1936-1939 (Box 7, Folder 84-86, Reel 4U)
    - Notebook on Hopi including botanical notes, 1938-1939 (Box 7, Folder 87, Reel 4U)
    - Notebook on Hopi and miscellaneous lectures and writings, 1939-1940, n.d (Box 7, Folder 88, Reel 4U)
    - Notes on contracted plurals and Hopi relational stems, undated (Box 7, Folder 89, Reel 5U)
    - Notebook on Kiowa and Hopi, 1933-1934 (Box 7, Folder 90, Reel 5U)
    - Notes on Maya hieroglyphics, 1929-1934, n.d (Box 8, Folder 91, Reel 5U)
    - Notes on Maya, Cholti, Quiche and Tsotsil, 1929-1936, n.d (Box 8, Folder 92, Reel 5U)
    - Notes on Maya-Quiche, 1931-1932, n.d (Box 8, Folder 93, Reel 5U)
    - Maya hieroglyphics: photograph, photostats, transcriptions, undated (Box 8, Folder 94, Reel 5U)
    - Notes made prior to Mexican research trip, 1930 (Box 8, Folder 95-96, Reel 5U)
    - Notebook on Mexican research trip, 1930 (Box 8, Folder 97, Reel 5U)
    - Notes on Menomini, 1940 (Box 8, Folder 98, Reel 5U)
    - Spanish-Mexican vocabulary list, undated (Box 8, Folder 99, Reel 5U)
    - Notes on connected words, undated (Box 8, Folder 99, Reel 5U)
    - Notes on various languages and their relationships, 1927, 1931, 1934, undated (Box 8, Folder 100, Reel 5U)
    - Notebook on linguistics, 1935-1940 (Box 8, Folder 101, Reel 5U)
    - Notes on linguistics and linguistic theories, 1938, undated (Box 8, Folder 102, Reel 5U)
    - Notes showing how "Tenting Tonight on the Old Camp-ground" would be rendered by non-native speakers of English, undated (Box 8, Folder 103, Reel 5U)
    - Notecards for Hopi dictionary, undated (Box 9, Folder 104, Reel 5U)
      The materials are open for research.
    - Language notecards, undated (Box 10, Folder 105, Reel 5U)
    - Bibliographic notecards, undated (Box 11, Folder 106, Reel 5U)
  - Writings by Others (NOT INCLUDED IN MICROFILM)
    - Angulo, Jaime de, and L. S. Freeland, "The Chontal Language," Anthropos, 1925 (Box 12, Folder 107)
    - Beaglehole, Ernest, Notes on Hopi Grammar, 1937 (Box 12, Folder 108)
    - Beyer, Hermann, "Apuntes Sobre el Jeroglifico Maya Muluc," Memorias de la Sociedad Alzate, 1926 (Box 12, Folder 109)
    - Beyer, Hermann, "La Cifra Tres en el Simbolismo Maya," Memorias de la Sociedad Alzate, 1926 (Box 12, Folder 109)
    - Bunting, Ethel-Jane (translator), "Ancient History of Yucatan," The Maya Society Quarterly, 1931 December (Box 12, Folder 110)
    - Carnegie Institution of Washington, "Pottery Discovery in Ancient Maya Grave," News Service Bulletin, School Edition, 1932 December 18 (Box 12, Folder 111)
    - Ceballos Novelo, Roque J., Direccion de Arqueologia: Guia para Visitar las Principales Ruinas Arqueologicas del Estado de Morelos: Tepoztlan y Teopanzolco, 1929 (Box 12, Folder 112)
    - Cordy, N., "The Meaning of the Maya Day Names," The Masterkey, 1931 December (Box 12, Folder 113)
    - Guerra, Juan, Arte de la Lengua Mexicana, 1900 (Box 12, Folder 114)
    - Hackett, Charles, introduction to unidentified work, undated (Box 12, Folder 115)
    - "Histoire Tolteco-Chichimeque," Part III, 54-58: "Bamberger Photos", undated (Box 12, Folder 116)
    - Kluckhohn, Clyde, "Variations Observed at Moencopi from the Hopi Linguistic Material Furnished by B. L. Whorf", 1937 December (Box 12, Folder 117)
    - Martinez Hernández, Juan, ed., Diccionario de Motul Maya-Espãnol, 1930 (Box 12, Folder 118)
    - Noyes, Arthur A., and Miles S. Sherrill, A Course of Instruction in the General Principles of Chemistry, 1916 (Box 13, Folder 119)